hey welcome to Brandon sanderson's
writing Science Fiction and Fantasy
lectures from 2025 today we're doing our
second week on character I do this as a
hybrid one where I do some lecturing and
a little bit extra Q&A because we lost a
week um to some technical difficulties
but I get to everything that I wanted to
get to today so come and join us for
week two of character hey we're going to
do a second uh um I almost said episode
hey welcome to the brand show um we're
going to do a second lecture on
character today um I will try to be a
little more liberal with letting
questions be asked um because um you
know there's um we we aren't going to
have a Q&A uh lecture for this one
specifically so you'll have to save
those questions and sneak them in but I
did want to get the second lecture on
character to you because last time um I
only got U kind of to the the really
core idea of motivation and that's not
really the presentation of the character
right like I feel the stuff we talked
about last time is the most important
thing to making a character kind of
function in a narrative sense but what
we didn't talk about is how you actually
present them and to the audience the
stuff we're going to talk about today is
actually what they would say is the more
important stuff this is the sort of
stuff they bond to that makes the
character memorable so it's it's kind of
interesting like behind the scenes I'm
really focused on all right what makes
this character have rooting interest
what makes this character Dynamic so
they're changing what makes this
character Proactive or how am I building
the story such that a character who is
not proactive doesn't impede the story
so that readers don't turn against the
character for impeding the story these
are all those things but today we're
going to talk about personality um and
things like that I I did want to throw
up a mention of iconic character
uh this is not my phrasing I got this
from Howard Taylor who got it from
someone else um and I want to take a
moment to mention iconic characters are
the phrasing I prefer to use for
characters who do not have character
arcs who do not necessarily change story
to story and there are a lot of these
sometimes they'll have a mini character
Arc in a given story but that AR that
Arc is not relevant to their entire
personal
these are characters whose stories are
written to be read out of order right um
oh hi baby
uh getting started early on writing your
stories
um
so um iconic characters are people like
James Bond is kind of the classic
example right uh James Bond um Dirk pit
who I mentioned before uh but it also
kind of goes to the baby sitters Club to
the um Hardy Boys to some things like
this those are the obvious examples but
you can probably think of stories where
a character's um personality and Arc is
not as important as their external art I
would say that in um in alant my first
published book Ray Odin has mostly an
external
Arc um and the idea with that character
being that you sometimes just don't have
a character uh changing now rayen has
what we call an apprentice Arc right
he's going up in understanding and
knowledge uh and so he does have some
movement on the sliders but he his his
um his conflict is mostly external this
is kind of key for iconic characters uh
the question like we we like competence
we like
proactivity we can really handle uh in
uh some genres character
where the competence and the uh
proactivity are such that we don't care
if the character's learning anything
sometimes we maybe get a little tired of
every character having to learn
something um and sometimes you just want
to watch someone pick up Bazookas and
blow things up and do a very good job of
it um and in these cases the question is
not will the character learn to use the
force in time the question becomes is
this this the time where the villains
are just so capable that our iconic hero
is unable to save the day in time Andor
what does it cost this character to save
the day in time and you can probably
think of um some stories that you have
very much enjoyed where the resolution
is bittersweet because the character was
extremely capable but capable enough to
save most people but not everybody and
these sorts of
things and so in in general I recommend
character artarts uh not a hot take
however there is definitely a place for
a character thought of as an iconic
character who's uh fighting against
something more external um they can be
very fun to read and they can be very
poignant right like I would argue that a
lot of um Agatha Christi novels are like
this and some of the really most
powerful Agatha Christi novels have
characters like curo who are not
necessarily changing but the emotional
journey to go through on that one book
even though you know you could read them
out out of order can be super poignant
and emotional and have a lot of depth
even though the story is not about you
know her cupo overcoming his individual
flaws sometimes he does have his
limitations and things like that that he
has to deal with so um I wanted to get
that out there kind of as a coda to last
week's um lecture before we talk talk
about kind of the three things that I
think are how you present a character to
the reader so we did all this work
behind the scenes now what do you do
well you want to be able to present
these three things personality
motivation and values right and I would
say these three things are
interconnected motivation is what does
the character want right person uh uh
personality is how does the charact
express what they want uh out of life
and values are what are they willing to
do or to give up in order to get what
they want um and I build them around in
my mind these kind of core ideas um and
so we're going to take these uh one at a
time uh we'll go ahead with the one in
the middle I should have uh reversed
those let's talk motivation we talked
about it last week but I want to give
you a chance to ask question on this and
to kind of dig into it um motivation I
would say is you know it's the first and
most important one for your character
your Discovery writers are going to find
it often while you're writing um the the
character moot motivation will grow out
of what you're trying to do with that
story and with that character um I am
often asking a bunch of questions and I
have that as the last bullet point in
order to find my character motivation
and I am usually searching for it a
little bit while I'm writing um I
believe I told you guys this but I
generally outline heavily my plot and my
world but I do not outline my characters
as extensively I then go to the story
and start writing them as I am searching
for these three things personality
motivation values and I'm exploring
different manifestations of how I could
express these things and as I'm finding
them I jumping back to the outline and
rebuilding the outline now that I know
who the characters are and I find that
if I don't do it this way that I either
just come up with all stuff and throw it
away or I um am very rigid with it and
then the character doesn't seem to have
um a life to them um and so U kind of
I've mentioned this before I had three
vins before I arrived at the VIN that
worked right I had two kaladin before I
arrived at the kaladin that worked dinar
was always dinar he worked on the first
try he just as who he is um like I the
dinar that you read about is the same
dinar in 200 uh2 who was the same dinar
who's in the story I started writing
when I was 16 so dinar is just dinar uh
too stubborn to be anybody else um but
this is I'm I'm hunting these things and
I'm asking myself some questions along
the motivation um and there's I I just
jotted down a bunch of these questions
that uh I'm asking myself kind of
naturally um as I'm writing uh one is
backstory what in this character's
history informs why they make the
decisions that they do right now this
can be tragic or not um not every
character needs a tragic backstory
but I feel like it's a pretty valid
thing to say that a lot of the decisions
that we make and the motivations that we
have come from what we learned when we
were younger and the T the people that
we have become as we've made decisions
what key decisions right um you know uh
influence this character so um I suggest
asking yourself kind of the hard
questions on this character right like
what um doesn't this person want people
to know about
them and how much that does that inform
the choices that they make not every
character needs something like this or
needs that exact question but most
characters need something like this um
what failure will they never
repeat and how do they interact with
blaming themselves for failure
some people interact with those things
in different ways uh you know flaws
hindrances limitations all of these
things kind of play into that um the
Classic Hollywood way of doing this is
to ask yourself what does the character
want why can't they have it what does
the character need and what must they
sacrifice to have that um and those kind
of four variations on those four
questions come up quite often
when you're uh looking at uh kind of
Hollywood uh Works um and things like
that
um with all of these questions I'm
asking myself the why one of the more um
the ways that
people I've asked a lot of authors how
they come up with characters and most of
them respond at some measure of instinct
and gut like we study plot more than we
tend to study character as writers um
but a lot of them you'll you'll press
them be like some of them use a dossier
this is a list of questions they ask
themselves about every character uh you
can find sample ones online everybody
has um you know their own take on it I
just gave you some of the ones I asked
myself some people like keep a list of
those to help them distinguish
characters I have a friend who looks
through a
magazine searching for a picture of a
non-f famous person just the ads and
stuff of somebody that like this is my
character and once they see see the
person then she knows oh this is how
they would act this is who they are um
and things like this um everyone has
their own methods but one of the key
things to make a character work is to
figure out some fundamentals of who they
are and what decisions they would make
so that you are able to extrapolate that
let me see if I can explain this better
uh and I'm going to use kind of an odd
metaphor you're used to that for me um I
get very
detailed mindbending questions about the
World building of the of the cosmere of
my books specifically how would this
intricate minute thing about the magic
inter act with this very obscure aspect
of Magic on another world I get a lot of
questions like that um I am often able
to answer those not because I have
considered that corner case but because
I have fundamental rules that the magic
for The cosmere Works upon so that I
know that if I answer that question here
I can answer it in a way that in the
future if I were to ask that myself that
same question not remembering I'd
answered it I will answer it in the same
way because I'm extrapolating from the
same core fundamental ideals that make
the magic system work I look for that in
my characters the idea being that I can
anticipate how this character would act
because of these few core things about
them so that um if they ever deviate
from this I know I need to make sure
that there's an explanation in text
because the reader will get a sense for
this um so motivation is just it's going
to inform the rest of this what do the
what do they want why do they want it
what about their backstory personality
or the things we talked about last week
in form why they want these things
questions about this before we go on to
personality which is kind of like the
veneer that you put on um this character
after you figured out their motivations
again this is the sorry I shouldn't tap
for on for here you go look at listen to
that ASMR pop pop pop pop you're going
to have so much fun with oh yeah Tan's
nodding it went Pop
um they will probably cut that for you
you can thank Donald wherever he went
he's not oh Donald's not here he he was
back at the office he had to do
something he had to do something else um
so well Donald eventually will cut that
out for you um let's uh go to some
questions ask me some questions how do
you establish villain motivations when
often it's just take over the world
right how do you establish villain
motivations uh when it's often just take
over the world uh let me quote Pat
rothus um my one of my favorite Pat
rothus quotes I'm sitting on a panel
with Pat and someone says you know like
how what do you do with this and he's
like well make sure not to do the one
where they all want to destroy the world
because who really wants to destroy the
world that's where all their stuff is um
so how do you establish villain
motivations and how do you make it so
that it's realistic um and this can be a
challenge right because it's been done
so many times um I would say that if you
can come up with key motivations that
cost this then you are going to get a
lot of mileage when I said the why
Magneto wants to potentially Destroy All
Humans and if not enslave them
why if you know Magneto you can answer
that right well Magneto was put in a
concentration camp he realized it was me
or them they will do the same humans
will do the same things to mutants in
the future therefore I have to strike
first and make sure I can never be put
in that situation again it's a
completely like you know kill all humans
and basically uh that's what he ends up
trying to do in the first X-Men film
he's you know he thinks it might not
kill them but then you realize his will
and just kind of goes forward with it
right um and that's just a horrible
horrible thing but you understand um now
you can have iconic villains kind of in
the same way that you don't understand I
often talk about um Lord of the Rings in
this example Lord of the Rings would
probably not be strengthened as a film
Trilogy or as a book series if you had
indepth knowledge of what sauron's
motivations are right saon in those
stories is an iconic villain whose job
is to
represent a giant terrible force that
has to be reckoned with that's totally
fine um to offset that tolken makes sure
to include Gollum who has a very
understandable motivation he's been
corrupted by the ring which is kind of a
representation of power and things like
that but it's what's corrupting um Frodo
it becomes very relatable in that
specific instance so you can see what
his motives are he just wants the ring
why because this force of evil has
warped him and he's really kind of
pathetic because of it you don't have to
when we talk um magism we'll talk about
external and internal logic um you don't
have to have external Logic for why you
know the the the motives of the ring or
why the power of the Ring corrupts
that's not you know uh internal logic is
usually enough meaning internally it's
consistent so uh how do you do this well
those are two kind of
extremes um where you can you can make
someone iconic or you can give them
something very relatable if the motive
makes sense but is taken to extreme a
lot of times villains are made with a
tragic flaw that without which they
would be a hero right and that flaw is
often that they're willing to go to
extremes
Magneto hey mutants are in trouble I
learned from the Holocaust that humans
will destroy the other with even less
reason in that case with no reason and
they'll do it here because they're
afraid of us um therefore I need to make
sure the immunes are protected he takes
it the step further so I'm going to
destroy them all first right um um so
there there's some some Clues on that if
all else fails make Sauron
sexy and hope it
works
is sorry I had to throw that in I'm
talking about this iconic hero and then
and then their stupid sexy saon um going
skiing with with Homer um H all right
all right uh what else what else we got
over here do you have any advice for
writing like non-human characters that
the main character does interact with
yeah non-human characters the main
character does interact with so uh one
of the keys to remember here and I don't
think I talked about last week is how
you treat a Viewpoint character and a
non- Viewpoint character is very
different in uh narrative and this goes
for your villain question as well if
you're willing to give them viewpoints
which you don't always want to do you
will instantly humanize through use of
viewpoint when we see through someone's
eyes we we get an in instant burst of
empathy usually for them um and from
there it depends on how relatable you
make their motivations even if they are
with like often your motivation can be
relatable and your execution can be
alien and it'll still work very well for
instance you know we all love you know
our family if the alien has a very alien
type of family it's like all of them are
my clones well that's an alien type but
we all understand loving your family and
so if you want to humanize them and make
them more sympathetic you make their
motivations very relatable even if the
manifestation is alien and showing
through their eyes if you're not going
to show through their eyes then usually
how we perceive the character will
depend on how the Viewpoint characters
perceive them unless you are doing the
reversal right if you are laying it on
thick you can flip it on its head often
times this is what you do with a
character who is like if you have a
character who themselves is unrelatable
and they see an alien and think oh
stupid aliens I hate them we will
immediately bond to the alien instead of
the character because you've already
expressed this character's values are
opposite from our own right um and so
are you going to use the Viewpoint uh
verer Veni in a fire upon the deep is a
fantastic place to go for oh you got it
right there I was looking it up like
those are books that really show to do
that well so what verer Vinci does very
well he's one one of the Masters of
Science Fiction if you like Dune you'll
probably like a fire upon the Deep just
it's a very different book but it has
that same sort of depth of World
building and kind of Epic scope and in
this he has an alien species which is
just brilliant um and the alien species
is they are a group mind not a h mind of
doglike creatures like four to five
individuals come together and they
become a complete individual and on
their own they're only fra ments they're
not smart enough to be a full individual
you would think this is completely
unrelatable but the moment you're
through their eyes the motivations are
very relatable and you just immediately
click with this group of dog creatures
that have been shattered and they have
one piece of a Great Hero who's part of
their you know like and it's so
interesting but it also super relatable
so that's one thing um the less you show
us and the less the main character know
the more sense of wonder which can be
scary Wonder or can be inviting Wonder
depending on your tone you will have the
more viewpoints you show the more you'll
instantly humanize um and so it really
kind of depends on what you want to do
um you're writing fantasy so you do want
or science fiction your alien characters
I would say to express something that
could not really work in The Human
Experience in order to be like otherwise
why are you having uh this this alien so
uh historically a lot of um them are
just to take a human attribute and to um
magnify them by 10 right these are the
kons they are Warrior Race these are the
Vulcans they're very um you know they're
very logical things like that but you
know that I would ask yourself that
question what's going to you're you're
going to go to this alien um and like
what makes them why couldn't you do this
with a human character and then how much
do you want to make them sympathetic how
much do you want to give them viewpoints
and things like that does that help at
all great uh other questions yeah right
here and then we'll hop back there um
how do you make background characters
distinct from each other yeah how do you
make background characters distinct so
this is going to be one of those things
you're going to have to practice a lot
and learn um I recommend one of a couple
of things right so um for all of your
characters even your Viewpoint
characters you don't need them as much
for Viewpoint characters I do recommend
some sort of visual signifier that the
reader can latch on to to remember them
until they are comfortable with their
personality whereupon this thing does
not have to necessarily be you know a
feature but if this is the the only
person in the group with glasses and you
highlight that every time it will help
them click uh right and if in the same
way they have a distinctive motivation
um this is what we kind of talk about
with quirks that just comes out is the
type that can come out naturally in
conversation you don't need both but
sometimes both are good but what you're
looking at is the reader is going to be
searching who is this again oh yeah this
is the person who just absolutely loves
um or who has a weird interaction with
water water is strange Robert Jordan did
this right how how you know it's the the
whole freman thing he took that to an
extreme for for a culture in his it's
like how this interacts to a cup of
water just sitting there how can you
just leave a cup of water like that
coming out repeatedly so it reinforces
now the thing you're going to deal with
with this in um in a book is this is
instantly going to stereotype that
character okay um because we don't know
them yet that's uh that's going to form
the stereotype you are going to either
in some books you leave that character
kind of as a stereotype of themselves
you try not to stereotype entire groups
this way but you can leave them and just
be like this is this quirky character
they don't have you know this is who
they are uh they're there for Comic
reliefs right relief um you know when
most people get stuck to the wall with
storm light they're like get me off
lowen starts proposing to the floor
right um this is who they are uh and
things like that and having that you're
going to want to move beyond that a
couple ways to move beyond that is
eventually give them a Viewpoint or to
give them a heart-to-heart with the main
character where you start to get some of
this stuff that you can't you know why
are you like this well maybe like this
understanding that sometimes it's just
your personality and not everything has
to have deeper meaning but you know why
you like this or what how does who you
are make you uh interact with the world
right um and then also if you're having
it be uh them representative of a
fantasy race or something I would
recommend making sure there's an array
of characters from that culture who you
let us see what are some cultural things
and what are some individual things so
not every uh not every Vulcan becomes
Spock uh and you know that's not a
criticism of Spock Spock needed to do
what Spock needed to do Spock needed you
to be able to go to this TV show that
you maybe have never seen an episode
before right Spock needed to be iconic
Kirk need to be iconic bones need to be
iconic you need to be able to come into
it watch them out of order know who they
are and for that reason all Vulcans kind
of needed to be spu uh because otherwise
you know there's too much there it's not
an epic fantasy story it's a half hour
TV program or a hour long how long was
the original Star Trek it was an hour
yeah um yeah an hour with a lot of ads
but an hour by the way have you ever
guys ever gone back and watched original
Star Trek and you're like the soft
filters the soft fil anytime there's a
woman on Scream it's like it's like it
really is it looks like like their
having their senior photos in high
school taken right and then it cuts back
to Kirk and he's just like flat you know
regular and then you go back and there's
a totally different lens zoomed in uh
you you know
like it's the con episode is great but
the soft filter uh in the con episode
anyway um so what the time that they had
is very different from the time you had
so do try to take that extra time um and
things like this but remember they'll be
remembered for their quirks first and so
you can lean into that and use that and
then you add depth over time okay uh
yeah uh how many characters should we
should we flush out in the story how
many characters should you flush out in
your story uh depends on a couple of
things it's an excellent question how
much space do you have and what sub
genre are you in and what type of story
are you telling all right so rule of
thumb the more viewpoints you add the
longer your book will get and that it
kind of is
exponential right um so one Viewpoint
very easy to write even a short story
from one Viewpoint right two main
viewpoints it becomes really you can do
it but it becomes much harder it starts
to have this magnifying effect um and
things like that I recommend just keep
in mind a few things the really good
book with one or two viewpoints in a
reader's mind compared to the really
good book with 10 viewpoints they like
equally much but this one for a writer
skill is 10 times harder so as you're a
newer writer if this is what you want to
love to write write that don't worry
right but as a newer writer if you're
choosing between projects being able to
control bouncing between two viewpoints
or doing one first person Viewpoint that
is really well handled the end results
quality is the reader is not going to be
like well you know some people do prefer
the big epics granted but those can be
equally good books but this one's
chances of spiraling out of control on
you are enormous so if it's your first
book I might recommend one or two
Viewpoint characters two most people can
handle it teaches you to swap and how to
balance chapters with two viewpoints
what you can do is when one is boring
you can cut to the
and you're used to this format because
of uh Network television which usually
use uses a plot b-plot and the reason
they do that is um like a character's
like and now I need to get from here to
here cut other characters arrive to the
place that they were going um and you do
all this and then cut and you're the
this character so you can cut the boring
stuff you can still do that in one
Viewpoint you just put a pound sign put
a blank uh line and they cut but there
there's some momentum that happens when
you're jumping back and forth uh
learning the two two Viewpoint narrative
is can be really handy uh for that
reason um however a couple other rule
rules of thumb the more people who um
the more plot lines you have the more it
it goes out of control as well so for
instance two
characters um who are part of like a
romance that are both in the same place
interacting with each other um does not
expand the scope of the novel as much as
two people on two different continents
working with different parts of the uh
of the World building with different
goals okay and so you can do that and if
but if you add like you're like I want
to do four characters but it's two sets
of two that's way easier than four in
different places uh uh coming together
um but that can be really satisfying
right so in Stormlight Archive I did I
did four right we have the kaledin um
plot line we have the Shalon plot line
we have the dinar plot line and we have
the zeth plot line and they're slowly
kind of intersecting and we have some
sub viewpoints to some of those for
instance we're doing we're doing adalin
viewpoints with d our viewpoints adding
adalin on actually helped keep the the
the book it made the book work way
better he wasn't in the original drafts
so having a second Viewpoint there that
I can take off some of this stuff and
add to him ended up helping and that
didn't expand the scope of the novel I
made that swap I took some of the scenes
that have been downar and I maybe added
you know 5% of the book to add an
entirely new Viewpoint character but he
was completely subsumed by another
character's plot Arc uh if that makes
sense um so just be aware like w of
Kings is 400,000 words okay that's what
it took me to do pretty well four
viewpoints and one of those zeth is
barely getting any okay um so there you
go Viewpoint clusters ask yourself how
many arcs how many viewpoints you're
going to have um and these sorts of
things and then I guess the other thing
I was going to say is uh your your genre
right if you're on a fast-paced thriller
with a lot of external conflict you have
much less time for introspection because
you have less time for introspection
you're going to be a able to do a much
weaker job with character arcs and
motivations than you normally would if
you are writing I'm reading um uh an em
Emily Henry book right now my wife likes
them do you guys like Emily Henry I it's
a the romance novel um and um every
chapter is just flirting right like
there's a plot but the plot the real
plot of this story it's actually very
good but the real plot of this story is
woman is around doing something she
accidentally bumps into guy that she's
totally not going to hook up with they
flirt forever and then break and then
she goes somewhere else and he happens
to be there too and he's like are you
stalking me no I'm not stalking you
flirt flirt flirt flirt
flirt break chapter next scene he's
there too right like flirt flirt flirt
flirt flirt right like that's how um uh
that's how those books go you have a ton
of room for
introspection uh in those things
particularly if it's like a first-person
Viewpoint which I think this might be
from the the woman's Viewpoint not
trying to do anybody else
she can spend so much time on you know
how she interacts with her sister how
she interacted with her mother because
you know the story is not the world is
going to explode and we have uh 7 hours
to stop it and we're having to and the
story is you know as soon as we get done
with this scene she's going to show some
up somewhere else and he's going to be
there and they're going to grouchily
flirt um and that's the that's the whole
book um
so there you are um I'll put a mild
content warning on that one that are at
BYU um I haven't gotten to any uh any
parts that wouldn't be wouldn't be more
than mild but uh I'm not I'm not to the
end yet so it might be more than a mild
content warning so yeah so there you are
um go ahead so annoying characters are
annoying to read how could I make keep
readers engaged and heaven forbid even
like that person how do you make people
like annoying characters and how do you
keep them breeding um well you've got
the tools uh that keep them breeding
part right it's um you
proactivity pacing um you know promise
progress like if you're making progress
the most annoying thing to a reader is
not a character being annoying it's a
character standing in the way of the
plot moving forward right they will deal
with a character that they in
individually find um annoying if the
story is moving now how can you minimize
that character being annoying well you
can have your Viewpoint character find
them annoying too and find ways to not
like if the joke is oh no I have to deal
with this person um right or it does
something interesting to the character
um otherwise it's like why do you have
this character if their only purpose is
to annoy the reader maybe that's not a
character to have right um most of the
characters that work that are annoying
like it's because of the impact on a
Viewpoint character or it's the
Viewpoint character realizing they're
going too far and trying to curtail
these things and you know working with
themselves like they're a little bit
more annoying at the beginning right
like donkey annoys
Shrek but we laugh because Shrek being
annoyed is funny right so we're less
annoyed by Donkey because than Shrek is
because we get to laugh at Shrek uh
right and you know shre gets to voice
the frustrations we have and then in
other places donkey is there to offer
some emotional heart which moves the
story along which we like so I guess I
would ask yourself what's the purpose of
your a Doan character there's definitely
some reasons for them all right way in
the back then we'll get to some of you
over here um in the same vein how do you
write a character that you just want the
readers to hate how do you write a
character that you just want the readers
to hate um so there's different levels
of hate there's the love you the ones
you love to hate um and love to hate
usually works when this character is
like like how what what do we love to
hate uh we love to hate a character um
who is
competent and all of these things but is
um at the same time just doing stuff
that is like loathsome uh that we love
to hate them because the loathsome stuff
they're doing is also not uh how shall
we say um it's not so bad that you feel
bad reading it does that make sense like
um and so a character we love to hate is
somebody like that right we who's the
best we love to hate
we yeah doofen Schurz we just love doof
Schurz right we just love him Thanos is
a better example right like what Thanos
is doing is awful right but like we he
moves the story along so much and we
don't have to watch a lot of it and the
heroes get to to face him down it's like
you know they're going to they're going
to save the world eventually so um how
else do you write a character that you
hate well make sure they interfere with
the heroes um they hit the heroes in
their weaknesses if they hit the heroes
in their limitations it's even more
right like if you hit Superman you you
take if you take kryptonite and you get
Superman oh we hate you if you exploit
the fact that Superman has a moral code
we hate you even more right um and so
just kind of look at make sure they're
hitting the heroes in the place that
they're vulnerable in ways that'll make
us um you know at really hate them it's
more than simple cruelty it's cruelty
that impedes the the people that we like
it's probably your best
bet um all right we're going to go over
here we'll go back there and then we'll
hop over here yeah how do you handle
character shifting motivations as
discover yeah how do you how do you have
character shifting motivations as they
discover new information it's an
excellent question because most books
that's what you want to have happen you
uh your character Arc is really about a
shift in
motivations um in fact the best
character Arts generally are when
someone's like really loves a character
art it's because Cusco has moved from
wanting his new Summer Palace to wanting
friends and protecting those friends
right and so how do you do this well
this is your job showing the the
progress right you establish the
motivation early and you either show
that it's shortsighted I need to get the
power converters you need to save the
the entire galaxy Luke about the power
converters like he doesn't really want
to get the power converters he's annoyed
by it but that kind of represents I have
to get back to ant you know I I can't
actually go on the Venture so you're
going to show steps and uh early on your
promise is this person's scope needs to
be expanded Bilbo we want you to go on
an adventure with dwarves and steal from
a dragon we don't want you to sit at
home and be peaceful I'm sorry so we
want your MO a to shift over time and uh
we want to show that the that you're
acquiring new motivations and slow
progress on that right and give us
something we want that the character
doesn't yet want show why it would be
good for them and show over time them
acquiring a new value which replaces
their motivations okay um now you can
backslide too you can go the other
direction um and in that case they're
acquiring you know a new value that is
detrimental to who they are and that's
replacing their motivations we haven't
really gotten the values yet but you can
figure that one out right makes sense
all right go ahead um so question kind
of what you're talking about about
introspection before if you're writing
from the Viewpoint of a character who's
like intentionally very introspective
and is getting distracted a lot and is
commenting on how do you still feel like
the plots moving forward always kind of
com okay so you've got a character who
likes lik to comment on everything
they're very introspective we call this
Naval gazing um in writing parlament uh
the character is Naval gazing they're
looking inward um uh
but how do you keep the plot moving if
this is this type of character uh lots
of ways you can do this um Bilbo's a
classic example of this right he's kind
of forced out into the world he would be
just sitting and thinking about which
cheese uh you know which cheese taste
the best on which given day um and then
he finds that he likes adventure to the
point that you know he writes a book
about it and later on he wishes he were
back on adventures so he's acquired a
new value um so one of the things you're
going to have to do is you're going to
have to use external forces to keep them
moving and pulling them back um or you
make their voice so darn readable and
interesting that we don't notice that
they're Naval gazing um this is the the
thing you will find in a lot of first
person
romance novels and or the snarky ya teen
girl protagonist right that because the
writing is so
interesting that you don't mind so much
like Jane atin one of the great writers
of all time um Jane Austin it's because
of and it's not even first person but
it's because of the voice of the pros
and the character that we are engaged by
scenes that normally don't feel like
they're moving the plot along very much
but we're there for the voice um and one
of the things that I should tell you
about like plot progress payoff right
like that's how you make a kind of
classic plot work remember not everybody
is there for
plot that's if you want a plot to be
engaging sometimes people are there for
voice hitch trier's guide of the Galaxy
you are reading hitch trier's guide of
the Galaxy for voice
so
promise progress payoff is not like this
is seventh on the list of important
things for that uh book series and if it
flubs it at some point usually it's done
intentionally because he was a brilliant
writer to service one of the things
earlier on the list the humor is more
important than whether the mechanics of
the World building makes sense um and
the kind of message is more important
and the voice is more important
animportant in those books one of the
reasons I like pret so much is because
he's able to balance these two things
and have a plot be important and some of
these voice um and things uh you know
like I think that balance for me works
better than it does in hitchhikers but
hitchhikers is brilliant and the fact
that you would like go this whole
lecture on plot uh progress payoff you'd
hand it to Douglas Adams to be like you
know throw it over his shoulder and go
write one of the best science fiction
books of all time means that people read
for different things and different books
do different things so keep that in mind
okay some books are about the
introspection you can lean into that you
can make it work but your voice is going
to be really really handy for that um
and kind of like if you can make it so
that introspection is relevant to what
the reader wants to be reading for that
given book and the the sub genre you're
going to be able to get away with more
of it in General Ed try to trim this
back and they're usually right okay you
usually need less of this than you think
but as writers we love it right we are
there for characters sitting in Naval
gazing for chapters on end because
that's why we write is the contemplate
the world and dance through flowers and
things like that but you know all right
okay right here
so yes it is you yeah you can't ever
tell sometimes I point yeah
um so how can you illustrate especially
like introspectively with an interal
monologue like the gradual either
Improvement or debasing of a character's
morals yeah um how do you show the
Improvement or debasing of a person's
morals so this this does go back to PL
uh promise progress payoff right this is
where like often times you will for a
character Arc show somebody being unable
or unwilling depending on the type of
character Arc to do something early on
and you present them other opportunities
through the story to achieve those same
things right that is why the um that's
why better off
dead deep cut starts with a character
trying to ski a hill and then the big
climactic ending moment he has to ski
that same Hill right and he's failed
every other time better off dead is a
parody of a teen Sports uh um drama
uh done as a comedy but it still uses
the same structure in the same way you
might show somebody making a good choice
early in the book that in the middle you
know what their choice would have been
but they're presented with the same
thing and this time they slide a little
the next time they slide a little just
make sure the reason for that value swap
is there that changing motivation we
understand why right um though it's not
handled brilliantly everybody's seen it
so episodes 1 2 and 3 are there to show
the debasement of an idealistic Jedi and
the point is showing the change and
values based on him falling in love and
the person that he loves um life being
worth more to him than the values of the
institution that uh that raised him
right and you see that over time again
can be kind of clunky but the arc is
there what George was trying to do was
there and it's a it's a good
illustration of this uh and so that you
know at the end when he makes the
decision you know to to go against Mace
Windu that it's not a decision he would
have made earlier and you've seen him
not make that decision but start to
think about it a little bit so uh there
you are any in this one and then we're
going to go to some more yeah right here
in the stripes um on your on your yeah
yeah you got Stripes
mhm are we going to have lecture like on
like more on romance or so hey what an
excellent
segue what an excellent segue um so next
week you'll have um you'll have some
guest lectures because I'm in
Hawaii uh yay um it's on a it's a
rioting retreat with all of my officers
so we're all going to Hawaii um it's
what we're spending The Wheel of Time
money on uh so uh they uh I consult on
the Wheel of Time television show and
they pay me like a hundred grand or
something and we're just gonna use that
and go to Hawaii um so me and Dan and
Adam and my wife and everybody will be
sitting up and you know sitting in
hammocks and thinking about all of you
back here where it's actually going to
be kind of warm next week I should have
gone you know last week when it was all
snowy so I could have but anyway uh Our
Guest lecturers are going to be uh Jen
and Becky um and um they are so I have
had a fun experience with them like I my
15ers class um often has uh people who
uh do not look like traditional students
shall we say that meaning they're old
people like me uh right like you go you
go in the class and you're like I you're
in your 40s and 50s uh and it's because
you know my class is an evening class
anybody can take it it's just based off
of you know uh how good your writing
sample is well it turns out that two of
the people there were more my age were
professional
novelists they had a bit of a leg up in
the submissions thing and they're both
romance novelists who wanted to learn to
write
fantasy uh and so they're both Indie
published uh they both earn uh I won't
give away how much money they earn but
they earn uh significant livings with
their writing like what you would
consider a good living um that I think
most of the people in this room be like
I would take that job um right um um
they're doing very well with their
writing uh they know Indie publishing
and they both write romance Romany being
the thing right now I ask them to uh to
adjust their lecture I often have them
in uh and usually they're in while I'm
here um so I've heard their uh their
lecture multiple times I asked them to
add a section on romance uh so that uh
because it is the big thing right now I
figure having two romance experts talk
about romance and about Indie publishing
because as I warned you I know Indie
publishing from the perspective of
somebody for whom uh Indie publishing is
skewed and
distorted um and so uh so yeah so next
week uh I'll just pass the romance uh
Buck along to Jen and Becky I've already
asked them to prepare that lecture and
theoretically uh you should have a good
time I know their other lecture I think
it's really solid just talks about Indie
publishing really well you seem very
eager to I was just curious what their
last name uh Jennifer it's Becky Monson
and Jennifer neelson Neil
Peele Peele Jennifer Peele yeah uh Becky
Monson and Jennifer Peele yeah uh you
can look them up and maybe check out
their books they both published the
books they were writing in my class um
they were fantasy novels but they're
really romance novels with a Fantastical
element so uh I can't take too much
credit but uh they did seem to really
enjoy the class they were a huge
advantage to the 15 person class just
having workshopping with other with
extra professional writers so um there
you are so that'll be the we are going
to try to record that hopefully we won't
have any hiccups but we'll see what
happens uh with that and you know and uh
and things so all right so Jennifer
Peele and Becky Monson next
week um all right so we talked a little
bit um um well we talked a lot about
motivation let's talk about personality
so personality is how you express the
things that you want uh for your
characters I'm not talking about your
personality um things like this so um a
lot of the stuff I was saying about the
side characters comes into play here but
you can if you want use one of the I
don't know if I want to call them pseudo
science we'll say science adjacent
personality profile quizzes that people
love that are usually letters and or
colors um pretending all people fit into
one of those totally not the same thing
as horoscopes um but people swear by
them I don't want to get in trouble I I
know some of you really love them um and
you're like I I an uh IED or whatever it
is
um I there might be a J in there
um really the thing to to keep in mind
is you can simplify this right so um
with your character how do they go about
getting what they want that's going to
be a big part of the personality meaning
are they aggressive about are they
passive about it uh are they one will
just jump out and speak up what they
want will they stay back and work it
into a conversation will they never
mention it um you know how do they
manifest if they love their family how
do they manifest that um some people
manifest that by you know how they take
care of people other people manifest
that by writing a check um and how does
your character Manifest this value or
motivation that they have and how can
the reader latch on to that once again
at the beginning every character is
going to come off as a stereotype mixed
with an archetype right they're going to
be like all right this is the Wallflower
who never speaks up for what they want
and lets everybody walk all over them
you will add Nuance as the story goes um
and if you want to you know start off
like with a main character you can just
out of the say yes is the W follower who
doesn't speak up for what they want
unless you do X and then they scream in
your face you can start with a
contradiction for a main character I
recommend against it generally for the
side characters but you can make that
their thing but start getting us into
this idea like your early promises are
who is this character how do they uh go
about what is the text going to treat as
a
flaw um that they need to overcome and
what is it going to treat as a flaw
right um what is it going to treat as
something that's just like we love the
fact that this character is like this we
don't want them to abandon that aspect
of themselves the text doesn't want them
to they have to work around it but
they're not necessarily going to abandon
it um and trying to get across the
personality of the character it
dialogue and the first actions they take
are going to be your keys to this
dialogue can do so much heavy lifting in
stories you have to watch out for Maiden
Butler have I talked about this before
yeah you what you don't want to do is
have them come up and say their
motivations but your dialogue can show
how they
express themselves and their motivations
and one of the things that I do
recommend that writers try is having
three characters in a scene and trying
to write a scene where they all like you
know want things and stuff like that
with no dialogue tags and no setting
descriptions yeah um and see how can you
make your characters distinctive with
three characters so it's not just a back
and forth some are interjecting it's all
messy it's not one two 3 one two 3 how
can you make it so that the reader never
loses track if you can learn this it
will strengthen your dialogue and it's
one of the places to find personality
for your characters
um you can use dial dialogue cues or
Viewpoint cues now and then they can be
overused but they can be useful Gambit
gets a lot of
mileage um out of having his a Cajun
accent and the way that he
speaks it can be like dialect can be
grading usually less is more in um in
books uh because you have to write it
out usually you want to give flourishes
and things like that but remember this
should still evoke something deeper
about the character um I recommend
against some of the ones that become
cliche uh for instance to show someone
intelligent traditionally diction uh you
know a lot of times it'll be like they
don't use contractions and they use
words that you know the $20 words that
nobody knows um you've probably seen
these before it does work be careful
though I um I've known some people who
are very intelligent you guys might know
that my college roommate was a guy named
Ken Jennings right uh is that a surprise
to some yeah some of you Ken Ken
Jennings I was there when he was winning
on Jeopardy and he would not tell us how
many he' won because he was under NDA
and we just watched and watched and he
kept winning and he kept winning and
finally he was able to tell us yeah I
won the whole season I have to go back
and keep filming that's how long I kept
winning right um
Ken does Ken uses contractions Ken
doesn't use $20 words once in a while
he'll throw one out when it's really
precise he's precise he uses the right
word not just a word to sound smart be
but because it is a better word and he
speaks when he's with other very
intelligent people he starts shifting
into a new language we can call Simpsons
quism sticks they speaks almost entirely
in Simpsons quotes I'm exaggerating but
the references and the kind of cutting
each other off because they know what
each other are going to say uh and then
the zingers of jokes and the sort of
twisting of phrases they do that a ton
that's how those very intelligent people
interface with dialogue and it's nothing
doesn't sound like Spock at all doesn't
sound like you're traditional well we
have a this much percent chance of this
and you know long word that nobody knows
uh I've met a lot of intelligent people
they don't talk like
that um but they do use rhetorical
devices in conversation meaning they
have been educated so they know how to
make a thesis statement when they start
talking they support with evidence and
then they wrap up with a conclusion even
if it is this is the best Simpsons
episode and I'll tell you why right like
um you know you know the quotes it's
this quote what's it like they PE uh
highly educated people will organize
their thoughts differently their
sentences will become more complex and
they will build off of each other uh
this is something I've noticed if you
can get that down in your diction you
will have a different kind of depth of
uh evoking this is an intelligent
character than Simply Having them not
use
contractions you will do some of the the
other stuff like there are times where I
like I you know I have a character who
just loves big words that's like an
aspect that's a little different they'll
use these and then people will make fun
of them they're like it's just a really
nice word listen to it like that's a
character attribute and that kind of
gets into the quirks finding a few
quirks that you can use for your
character and if those can manifest in
their motivations a little bit they can
relate to them they can come out in
their diction and their
Viewpoint uh those are the quirks that
will really uh Drive pull a reader in um
and it depends on your sub genre um and
you know your mileage may vary uh David
from the reckoners which is one of the
book series I've written being really
bad at
metaphors it worked wonderfully right it
really did work wonderfully um and
readers responded to it very well um I
tried something s similar in the Fugal
Wizards uh handbook for surviving midal
England where the guy's just like
raiding everything out of star values
and it didn't work as well right uh and
his Viewpoint and so um you know one one
felt very natural to David why why it
felt very natural to David is he is his
personali he jumps into things before he
thinks them through that's kind of a
core attribute of him he will jump into
metaphors without thinking of what the
metaphor means and he just has to come
up with something and his brain works in
a different way and he just says it and
it only makes sense to him it actually
reinforces his primary character trait
the other just felt tacked on it felt
like quir for courir work sake I felt
like I I it worked better than um you
know than its biggest attractors but it
is a weaker one for that reason and and
hopefully that can explain to you like
having your quirks like
reinforce somehow your theme and your
character in uh in certain ways is going
to be helpful for
you uh let's do some more questions so
uh who else wants to ask questions about
characters yeah back there uh I'm big
fan of the co brothers and how they like
write characters yeah their side
characters are very good just kind of
like giving
you
very so the question is um really likes
the Cohen Brothers um and Cohen Brothers
are very good at Side characters um and
making everyone very distinctive how can
you translate that uh to Pros so uh what
makes a Cohen brother film work is that
it's in like a parody imagine a parody
is like a 100% exaggeration and a Cohen
Brothers film is a 10% exaggeration
instead uh because you're doing just
that slight exaggeration and you're
making it a loving exaggeration instead
of um a la point at and laugh that
exaggeration kind of exemplifies uh
things like this and so because of that
they'll take a certain interesting piece
of diction and and they will exaggerate
it by 10% um and they will take like
character motivations and they are
larger than life they are exaggerated a
little bit uh in order for even for the
life that someone's living even if it's
a normal life right uh they exaggerated
by 10% um and they allow the humor of
situational comedy to creep into the
drama and then they hit you with the
drama with a with a a kind of a left
hook it's a very
specific individual and kind of
brilliant mixing of these things if I
were going to try to do this in Pros I
would pick something that looks
linguistically interesting on the page
and I would exaggerate it by like 10% um
and how you're going to work that's
going to depend very individually on you
there are certain things you can get
across very well and certain things that
would be a little bit harder but I think
you could figure it out so exaggerate
the dialects just by like 10% um and
then make sure you have that mixture
like they try really hard that as the
situations Get Ridiculous the
motivations of the human the the
protagonist are so relatable that you're
able to push through and so I would I
would have that little extra
Ridiculousness of a story um like don't
go as far as
pratchet but it's kind of like that sort
of thing he's doing the same thing he's
just he's turning that dial up to 75
5% uh instead of to 10% that's what I
would recommend I've never sat down and
actually tried it uh probably the close
I get is from some of the Hoy uh story
narratives where he does kind of the
same thing like when you're when you're
reading Tres some of things are dialed
up like 10% about character
personalities and the way that people
act um where you can kind of tell hoy's
exaggerating a little bit so that's what
I'd recommend yeah over here and then
we'll come up here you've been raising a
lot sorry yeah I did see you we get
there and then come down here have you
read theater I have not read the sun
eater okay I have to PHR this a
different way then uhhuh um thoughts on
like characters that if we're not in
their own Viewpoint would totally be the
villain yeah thoughts on characters if
we're not in their Viewpoint they would
be the villain um this is a whole host
of types of sto of story a whole a whole
genre um what are your thoughts well
that's what books are really good at
books are really good at showing You
Through The Eyes of somebody and
expressing their own motivations in
their own eyes I don't think that we
need to spend a lot of time on sips for
that because it's a natural strength of
the Gen it's actually much harder in
film than it is um in books because you
have that natural Viewpoint like as
we're seeing through someone's eyes we
understand their rationale um just make
sure that their motivations are really
sympathetic and you're probably going to
be okay um and you know you can also
have in a in a book if you want you know
someone he would be a uh or she they
would be a villain in another story you
can show that they didn't intend these
consequences and had actually planned to
try to make sure they didn't happen but
some freak accident made made it occur
right and so there were casualties when
but you can also show that they think
that if they don't do what they're
trying to do the world will end or
things like that like you have so much
power to explain and rationalize the
Viewpoint character that I would argue
that a whole host of stories that we all
love the characters would be seen as
villains externally um because uh but we
have we have extra information from the
Viewpoint so yeah all right go ahead um
for like a a pretty beginner writer
specifically um if you want to tell a
story that focuses around a group of
people but you have a main Viewpoint
like maybe like five people um what do
you think is the easiest way to to
um uh help them all stand out but not
like get into nitty too much yeah yeah
make a medium large cast of characters
all stand out um contrast is your friend
here um being able to have two
characters in a situation where they
will talk about how they'd make opposite
choices we'll segregate them in our mind
into the person who would do this and
the person who would do that um and by
putting them together in situations and
showing how each of them act now again
this will start stereotyping them in
fact you can think of how any ensemble
cast of a um of any show or book starts
off as all right this is the tough one
this is the the sneaky one this is the
the one who's openhearted right whether
it's whether it's lost or whether it's
um the you know the Lord of the Rings um
the you know the fellowship and then
they get more time to uh kind of break
out of that mold over time but it's that
contrast right like let's look at Lord
of the Rings um Boromir is the one who
wants the ring gimbley wants to hit it
with his X right there's a contrast
Gandalf refuses it and is terrified of
it nobody else is but Gandalf is
terrified how they all respond to this
one simple thing um you don't want Mary
and Pippen to get it cuz they would lose
right like it's just you know how they
would all treat the ring and you build
from that that contrast is absolutely
your most important thing in uh in in
giving us our initial kind of feel for a
for an ensemble
cast
yeah um go
ahead if you're sign posting like a
betrayal what's a good way to do that
signpost a betrayal it depends on what
kind of betrayal it is and doing the
Betrayal is signposted by having the
trader say well I'm going betray them
that creates suspense rather than
mystery right uh and what emotion are
you looking for from this um and like
what are your what kind of sign posting
you are you looking to do is this a
betrayal of a of a dear friend well you
start off by showing the friendship and
why but then you have to subtly indicate
the shifting of
values um so that when the actual
betrayal happens or if it's someone
who's been sneaky all along and is just
there to betray someone you want in that
case to be able to look through and find
all the clues and one of your best
things you can do is have a um a six
sense moment where when your reveal
happens the main character thinks of all
the things that they should have seen
that were the clues uh not to spoil the
six sense but there's a moment at the
end where it's like here's all the stuff
you missed and you're like oh I saw all
that uh and it was right there those
sorts of moments are really handy um but
it depends on if you want mystery or
suspense if you want shock uh what
emotion you're looking for sense what do
we got all right we'll go here and then
uh to the the the
baby baby's got a question how do you
make sure dialogue doesn't drag on how
do you make sure dialogue doesn't drag
on um breaking it up does wonders uh
readers eyes start to glaze over if one
person is talking too much but the same
information cut up with people
interjecting and chatting helps Aon make
sure that all the GRE characters are
participating we want to avoid a
Socratic dialogue uh as good as they are
for what they're doing a Socratic
dialogue is guy talks about how awesome
he is and another person asks really
leading question to let them answer it
in a uh in a really interesting way um
that starts to read like a soapbox essay
uh where the character is not
participating characters disagreeing
characters kind of having a little fight
um through their dialogue uh and
treating it bit like an action scene
will all help speed it up and then good
oldfashioned screenwriting um adage in
late outter
in laid out early is just a you want to
start any given scene as late as
possible to the interesting things
happening to like and you want to get
out as early as possible after the
interesting things happen what are the
interesting things that's you know but
the just the adage of can I can I get
this closer to the the parts that are
really going to be uh succulent and
great um is is a good adage to have so
usually readers prefer dialogue to
narration usually so as long as it's
Snappy and working you obviously want to
balance a both in most books but usually
they prefer it all right um how can I
write a character that's influenced by a
background that I've never had how do
you write a character how do you write
so there are entire sequences in fact I
think writing excuses has done multiple
episodes about um you know writing the
other is what they call this um so
there's a couple of things and this is a
big question so we'll end here uh we'll
do I'll be on this for 4 minutes um so
number one reading primary sources is
just enormously helpful we live in a
wonderful age where everybody uh
everything you'd want to read about
somebody is written about uh and in fact
one of the best things that they'll do
is they'll often write about here is
what media gets wrong about X I am a um
forensic scientist here is what people
get wrong about forensic science that'll
tell you so much um the you know what
what do people get wrong about uh living
as a transgender person in the United
States read that it will tell you what
do media get wrong uh and things like
that will tell you so much um so read
primary sources number two remember that
people are you know characters are human
beings and any given human being doesn't
fit their mold perfectly so you can
write a character who doesn't fit their
mold in some ways as long as you're
getting other things right there will be
some things that are just individual to
that character character there aren't a
lot of women like spener right um you
know but there are some and so just
remembering that and making sure that
you're getting some things that are
common to the experience and some things
that are individual character and making
sure you're highlighting the individual
ones it's kind of different to that
character uh having uh primary sources
read your story uh and tell you what
you're doing wrong like um Skyward got
so much better because I went and got
fighter pilots to read it and I said all
right what am I doing wrong they're like
oh this this and this and uh you know
some of them were extensive rewrites um
but the the book got so much better
because I had actual fighter pilots tell
me what it feels like and it turns out
them reading my Pros trying to stumble
through using primary sources uh has
been super helpful a disassociative
identity order uh is another one like um
like I needed a ton of help with that um
and a lot of times you can't tell the
ones you're doing a good job with and
ones you're doing a bad job with until
you get some of those reads um because
some things uh that I thought I that I
was confident in I turns out people
right like yeah that matches mine and
having a variety of reads right like you
can get three or four people because
again people are individuals living with
this associ identity disorder is
different for each individual and so
getting I I I had three different people
I believe it was read um for us and you
know as long as things were were
conceivable that a character with this
could do this and I was hitting the
Hallmarks and other places then it
worked um and ask yourself you know in
some of these uh cases you want to be
careful not to be doing
damage um right and a lot of the times
like that's the the the biggest uh worry
um if you want don't you if you're
wanting to write someone's um life
experience and um you are one of the you
know like in my case I'm a very popular
author I'm one of the few people who a
lot of people will read in a year if I
get something wrong and perpetuate a
stereotype it can just be devastating to
the readers are like you know like
everyone thinks this about us um we got
a reader on trust the emerald scene and
they're like everyone gets this wrong we
can't lip read nearly as well as TV and
books make us and it actually causes
harm for us because people just assume
we can follow a conversation when lip
reader is just not capable of doing what
uh what media's made it I'm like oh I
don't want to make that worse because it
makes their lives just a little bit
harder when everyone assumes that they
can lip read so in that case having that
authentic Source um and so what we do is
if it's somebody we go out for that we
actually pay them
uh and there um there are some people
who this is part of their job and they
tend to be very good at it as a newer
writer you may not be able to do that
but you still can ask on forums and
things and and have people look at the
specific scenes and give you some
feedback uh the authenticity will make
your story better and every case where
one of these has come up and I've
changed it and stretched further my
story has been better for all
readers not just uh for those and if you
want to know why go watch the 99%
invisible podcast on curb cuts to kind
of understand how
learning about something like this can
improve everybody but anyway there's my
uh thing thank you for that question I'm
glad you asked it I'll be gone next week
and we'll do sanderson's laws of Magic
the week I get back so
[Applause]